started.
Thanks. Right. Good evening everyone.
I'll now call to order this special work
session of city council for Tuesday,
June 17, 2025. Um this is a
non-legislative meeting, so it is a
special one. Uh this meeting and its
participants are being recorded. Uh we
will take public comments at the end of
the presentation this evening on topics
related to tonight's presentation and
comments are limited to three minutes
per speaker. It must begin with the
speaker's name and block of residents
for our meeting record. Um I will begin
with the roll call of members. Uh Mr.
Harris is not here tonight. So I'll be I
will be calling the role. Councelor Amed
here. Councelor Royo here. Councelor Kle
here. Councelor Craig here. Councelor
Diaz here. Councelor Hirs
and I am President Bay and I am here.
Councelor Hirs is excused this evening.
I'll now turn it over to city solicitor
Barry Handwicker to start our
presentation. Uh good evening. Pleasure
to be here. And um this is a followup to
our meeting on June 1st when I I gave a
presentation regarding this process and
talked a little bit about the how we got
here. uh what home rule is, why we're
doing it. Um and and I'd like to start
just with a little refresher uh real
short on those. So, the charter itself
mandates that certain items be covered
in what's called an administrative code.
Um provisions for the exercise of a
control function for the management of
finances, enumeration of departments, um
offices, authorities, boards,
commissions, and other administrative
units of the city, their scope of
responsibility and internal procedures
for excuse me, internal procedures for
adoption, budgeting, accounting and
financial policies, purchasing and
acquisition procedures, policies and
procedures related to HR matters. You'll
note when you look at the screen in your
materials that three of those topics
um are specifically in tonight's
material packet. Um
one of the things u to remember is that
we already have most of the information
that you're going to see tonight. Most
of it is already either in existing city
code. So remember we have a code of
ordinances codified code of ordinances.
A lot of it is already there. Um, some
of it is in the third class city code
and some of it's internal policy that
we've already been following and now is
going to be codified as required by the
home rule charter. There are some new
items um that are being included and
I'll discuss tonight why we're including
those new items as well. Um,
and then one last thing to remember um
with home rule we can do anything not
prohibited by law.
And the concept of that that's why
that's important is that doesn't mean
that you have a code that covers
everything. We're gonna and I remember I
I talked a little bit about um reading
through the charter and as we as we move
into the code in the first page of it
and we're presenting these articles are
not in order. We're presenting the ones
that we think are we divided these
equally in half. Um and so obviously two
of these five topics are going to be
covered in the next section. um when we
start with that in uh August. Um but the
the ones tonight deal primarily with the
financial lens and you're about to un
start going through some of the things
that are newly required by the charter
which is the capital budget which is
coming before you very shortly followed
by a much earlier round of the budget.
Um, so it sort of ties in. So you're
going to get sort of a refresher course
on a the budget process that the charter
lays out and b some of the financial
issues that go get associated with the
budget. Um, but one of the things to
keep in mind is in in terms of why that
rule is so important is the enumeration
of powers, which we're going to get to
shortly.
um follows what we've had for many many
years here in the city and follows what
the charter says which is council is the
legislative body. The mayor's office and
the administration executes and
administers the ordinances that are
adopted by council. So the fact that
there's not an ordinance on something
doesn't mean you don't have the ability
to do it. If it's legislative, it means
you already have the ability to do it by
ordinance. and through both the charter
and the code will be you've already got
a procedure for how you pass an
ordinance. That doesn't mean you can't
adopt additional ordinances setting
forth new procedures for different
things and that's part of the beauty,
right? So when you look at
municipalities that have home rule other
than um I'll use Pittsburgh as an
example um which has a close to like
200page administrative code. They also
deal with a budget that's a little bit
different than ours. Um, a population
that's different than ours. And they
they've over time legislated just about
everything procedurally because they've
adopted different procedures. So you
still will have the flexibility to do
that at all times going forward. And you
have the ability to change whatever you
adopt here as the administrative code at
any time by ordinance. So, it's the
greatest form of self-governance and the
most power that can be given to a
legislative body in Pennsylvania. Um, so
that's the that's the true beauty of
what the home rule charter has done for
the city. So, as we go into the first
page, um, we're going to start with uh
what I'll do here is is sort of
summarize the provisions, why they're
there, and where they've come from. I
understand you haven't read that this
yet and that's quite frankly intentional
so that I can explain to you where it
came from so that when you read it in
detail over the next couple of weeks um
and study it you understand why we put
it in that doesn't mean that we're bound
by it. It's this is simply a starting
place based on my 35 years of working as
a municipal solicitor uh almost that
entire time having some contact or work
for the city working with other uh
municipalities. These are just a
starting point where I think it's best
practices good recommendations that
doesn't mean that you have to follow it.
This is simply a place to give you to
start working on this document. So the
first thing is if you've looked at a lot
of state legislation and even some of
our own city legislation is we usually
give the ordinance and this will be
ultimately an ordinance a title. Uh in
this case I chose administrative code of
the city of Lancaster. I think as I
mentioned in June 1st there's probably
only really three choices.
Administrative code, administrative code
of the city of Lancaster and city of
Lancaster administrative code.
As we often do with legislation, we put
in a series of definitions. There's a
couple of these I just want to point out
because they um
they relate to some of the provisions
you're going to hear tonight that may be
new um and different than what has been
existing under either city code um the
third class city code or your existing
practice. First of which is you're going
to see a definition of conflict of
interest. Um the reason that's in here
and you're not going to get necessarily
get to it as much tonight. There is a
provision we'll get to a little bit
tonight, but uh
right now the state ethics code applies
to a limited number of municipal
officials um and doesn't isn't as broad
perhaps as um some other things. And
most of what you're going to see in the
definition of conflict of interest is
common sense, right? like if if if
things that are not supposed to be
produced because of law, i.e. criminal
in criminal information, child
information, things of that nature,
every city official should be bound to
not disclose them, including council
members. So, that's one of the reasons
that's included here. Um, you'll see a
definition of environmentally preferable
product. So, one of the things we're
going to talk a little bit about later
tonight is uh some new procurement
concepts, and this relates to one of
those. Um, lowest responsible bidder is
one. We've used this term many times,
but uh the last phrase of this
definition typically lowest responsible
bidder is the bidder who meets all the
qualifications who has submitted the
lowest bid and we award contracts based
on that. Um to legislatively require and
provide that if you are a proposed
bidder and you have a history of
fraudulent or irresponsible behavior in
previous dealings with the city, you
cannot be a lowest responsible bidder.
So this is sort of helping to weed out
those who may not have proceeded and I
don't have any to use as examples right
now but in the future those who who may
not be honest with us in their
submissions or we have bad dealings with
would not be able to bid again. So it's
it's meant as a deterrent
um to contractors to make sure they tow
the line correctly.
And then again uh sustainable
procurement which is similar to the
environmental definition we referenced
before and we'll talk about that again a
little later. So as we move into now
article two um powers and divisions of
powers
sections one two and the first part of
three are really a reiteration of what's
already in the charter and what we've
already been doing for decades and
decades principally since we adopted an
optional form of um uh third city
governance uh many many years ago which
is the legislative power is that of
council and the executive power is that
of the mayor. Um, what you'll see in the
second paragraph
of section three is nothing really new.
What's brought there is moving what's
already in your city code regarding the
emergency powers of the mayor to declare
and powers to declare a state of
emergency. Those are both in your
charter and they're also in chapter 136
of the city code. So, we're basically
trying to make sure we don't repeat
things. And when you repeat things,
obviously you have chance for
inconsistency. So they're being
incorporated in here. Um the fourth
paragraph, the third full paragraph,
excuse me, in in the section of powers
of the mayor, there's some things now
that the mayor does that are authorized
by the third class city code. They're
not specifically referenced in the
charter, but they've been added here.
Again, uh assuming that perhaps the city
wants to continue the practice of having
um the mayor have the authority and
power to take acknowledgements and
instruments in writing to the business
of the city and the authority to
solemnize marriages and the authority to
administer oaths and affirmations as the
city business. So it's just again making
sure it's clear that the mayor can do
that assuming that this council wants
the mayor to be able to do so.
So, article four, which deals with
salaries of elected officials. The
charter does contain a provision that
requires that the salaries of elected
officials be set by ordinance. What the
charter does not do is say when, which
leaves open when do we do this? And
currently the third class city code ties
that into
uh certain times for submitting
petitions and paperwork to be
candidates. And the concept behind the
provisions in the third class city code
is to make sure that everybody who might
want to consider running for the mayor
has the ability to know what the salary
is uh before they a file their and or
any elected position file their papers
and b that we don't get sort of the
funny games that could happen right
which is now because the salary is say
low uh and now two weeks after their
deadlines to file council who has four
members running for council decides to
change its salaries. So what what I've
put in front of you in in sec in article
four is what the current third class
city code currently provides which
governs that date and protects from both
of those occurrences.
So article five requirements of elected
officials regarding confidential
information. This is what I mentioned
when I talked about the definition of
conf confidential information. Um really
this is cottifying common sense,
responsibility and decency. Um I I also
anticipate that there are provisions
throughout the charter where provisions
of the ethics code could end up being
incorporated or brought and this is one
of those places.
So now we move to some of the bigger
sections. Um and article 11 is budgets.
The first parts of this section one and
the fir and section two are really
repeats of the charter. And the reason
we're repeating them here is because
remember what I told you the charter
told us we have to do in the
administrative code. Even though the
charter covers the process for budgets,
the charter also says we have to have a
provision in the administrative code. So
it's bringing that forward here. Section
three is also information that's
currently in the charter, but we're
showing it in a what we think is a
little bit easier way for council and
members of the public to understand,
which is the time frames for adopting
both the budget and the capital budget,
sort of in a tabular form. Um, all this
information is in the charter, but you
have to read through a lot of words to
figure it out. And so we're trying to
put the dates in a way that can be used
as a roadmap by everybody uh for years
to come.
You'll notice that you know we have
provisions for budget hearings both for
the budget and the capital budget. Again
these are required by the charter. So
these are just carry forwards um where
we start to fill in what are things left
by the home rule study commission to
council. Appropriations and transfers is
one of them. The provisions you have in
front of you are exactly what we've been
practicing under um and what are in the
third class city code which is how we
make appropriations and then how we have
transfers or what transfers are allowed.
um keeping in mind that only minimal
transfers between departments are
allowed without council approval. So the
continuing the check and balance that
while the mayor and the administration
enforce and execute the ordinances the
budget is still councils and there's
that there's that work together
requirement and council ultimate
approval of changing a document that
they already approved namely the namely
the budget orders.
So then we move to article 12 which is
finance and accounting. And again a lot
of these things seem um and are common
sense but without legislation you can
end up in dispute. So first we want to
make sure that the director of
administrative services is required to
deposit city funds and and Tina if you
don't we have a problem but we want to
make sure and otherwise the ethics
commission which is now forming and
going to meet is going to have code
provisions that will deal with you. Um
but the director of the department of
administrative services shall deposit
all city funds, taxes and other revenues
into such financial depositories as
approved by the mayor in the name of the
city. The next sentence is something new
and this one is again best management
practices that we're suggesting which is
the sh city should seek to maintain as
few bank accounts as possible and that's
an internal control mechanism. the more
the more accounts, the more ability
there is obviously for people with
access to move money. And it's a it's an
it's a pretty strong internal control
function going back to my days in my
accounting classes in the 1980s.
Um the next section then on city funds.
So what you have here is really a
description
of the types of funds. And these are
funds that we've been using and have
been authorized but have never really
been defined or described. And so this
will hopefully help you future council
members uh future and members of the
public in understanding when the words
funds are utilized and discussed at the
budget pro during budget time and during
the course of the year.
what we're really talking about. And you
know, one thing to keep in mind as you
go through the funds is a fund is not
the same thing as an account.
A fund is an accounting term. So we can
have one account,
right? But it could actually hold fund
money from several funds, right? The
funds are how we're accounting for
money. The account is the physical place
where the money's kept. Now, that
doesn't mean we might not have a
separate account for each fund, and in
many cases we will, but legally it
doesn't mean that they have to be one
and the same. Um, so you're going to see
a lot of definitions and descriptions
here. General fund and and I think
that's the one everybody's the most
familiar with. Obviously, it serves as
the general operating fund of the city.
Special revenue funds um are funds that
are utilized with respect to specific
revenue sources that are restricted for
specific purposes. debt service funds. I
think most of you have had some um
introduction to that through the debt
ordinances that have come your way over
time. But again, that's how we're
dealing with the repayment of debt.
Capital project funds. Um these are
funds specifically set aside for capital
projects where they have restricted and
committed access, you know, for
particular capital projects,
proprietary or permanent funds. Um so
again these are used to account for and
report resources that are restricted to
an extent that only earnings and not
principal can use to supplement uh city
programs. Um again these are the types
of funds that can be utilized not
requirement that we have them. This is
more about hey this is the way your
accounting system may ultimately place
funding. Um there are two types of
proprietary service uh proprietary funds
that are typically dealt with. one um
you're probably pretty well familiar
with at this uh this time which is
enterprise funds and those are the funds
where we're talking about um a segment
of the city operations that really
functions as an independent sort of
entity from an accounting standpoint
wants to account for its expenses its
revenues typically these are tied to
places where we have user fees specific
user fees that are funding operations
the biggest examples of this are your
water fund and your wastewater fund
those are enterpris funds
um internal service internal service
funds are funds that are used to account
for loans or transactions between city
departments. So another type of
accounting fund that can be utilized
that you might see in place or in your
audit or in your budget process. And
then obviously we have fiduciary funds
which are things like your pension
funds. Um we also have some other types
of funds that are authorized under law
and they've been inserted in here
private purpose trust funds and
custodial funds and again the
definitions are here but the concept
here was rather than funds are utili the
word fund is utilized throughout many
documents and there's no place where
it's been summarized for city staff uh
and city council members and residents
to understand. So this is a place to
codify what we're all talking about when
we talk about those funds
and and quite frankly many of those are
the we've already been utilizing them.
Uh it's past practice. We uh the
auditors have been referring to these in
the audits you get every year. Um this
isn't new but it's new to be in sort of
legislation of the city.
Section three deals with investments. So
the next series of of sections, if you
recall, the charter requires us to talk
about financial policies and management.
And so the the next sections um and Tina
is here along with the mayor. Um these
are
essentially policy statements and
projections of best management practices
related to some significant financial
dealings of the city. Right? So the
first is investments and you know the
the the goals and purposes are set out
in this section. Um the objectives of
what investment should be are set forth
in this uh section. Um the standard
that's used to judge which is the same
standard our auditor uses. So again,
it's not new, but it's not all of it is
new, but it's about taking a lot of the
things that this city has done
and codifying them and now being able to
hold everybody accountable to be in the
same place, right? Um,
and it directs and off and and
authorizes the mayor and other bodies
responsible for the management of funds
by the city to adopt and maintain
policies related to this. you're going
to see at the end there's a significant
reporting requirement.
So
funds can't be invested and then not
reported. That's an internal control and
that's the balance between again you
control the budget as council. The
mayor's executing on that ordinance but
there has to be reporting back. Um the
types of investments these are are
series of investments that are fairly
standard investments for municipalities
to enter into. Um there's a there's a
series of guidelines that are put out
for government entities. Um these come
right from them. These are the these are
the types of investments that are deemed
to be best practices investments for
municipalities. Um and there's a list of
about nine of them here. Um, and then
there's a series of uh we talk a little
bit about the types of things that are
ineligible
so that we're we're again starting to be
clear about what is and what isn't
allowed. You know, the the reality here
is municipal investment is conservative
in general, right? That is I mean you
would not invest most people around this
table would not invest their money
identically with the way the city is
required. And why is that? Because
you're stewards of somebody else's
money. It's not your money to take risk
with. It's your money to invest
prudently for the benefit of 60,000
residents. So the standards here are not
like, okay, well, we're going to go
invest in this necessarily right away in
the stock market and go into sort of,
you know, higher risk investments.
That's not the concept here. You're
already, the city's already been
authorized to invest money and has done
so for years in various funds and
various ways. The key is now defining
what is sort of the the guidelines by
which we do it and and that's what um
the investment provisions are supposed
to set forth. You'll note that section F
talks about reporting. Uh and here what
we're suggesting is that the director of
administrative services provide to the
mayor and city council quarter annual
reports providing a clear picture of the
status of the city's investment
portfolio. Um broken down to you know
individual securities um average life
and final maturity of the investments
coupon discount or earnings rate par
value advertised book value and market
value. Percentage of the portfolio
represented by each investment category.
confirmation the portfolio portfolio
complies with applicable law. Uh
discussion regarding non-compliance and
description of city funds, investments
or programs that are under management of
contracted parties, including lending
institutions. I'd like to say I take
credit for coming up with that, but I
didn't. Um uh director of administrative
services working with again um
governmental agencies responsible for
financial reporting uh has gleaned these
as the best practices and suggested
So the next section moves on to
borrowing
and the city's authorized under the
local government unit debt act. Remember
that's one of the acts I sort of
referenced in the definitions to borrow.
But again here this is following the
charter and saying you're supposed to
have sort of some policy objectives
built into the into the code that guide
both council and the administration as
you move forward with borrowing. And so
uh again the objectives of debt and debt
management policies here the mayor with
council approval based upon the advice
and director of administrative services
is to issue and maintain a debt
management policy. So what you're saying
here is mayor you need to go and come
back to us with a debt management policy
that we must approve.
So you get the final control on how
we're going to manage our debt. um the
those policies, you know, in in section
B list a whole lot of things that should
be in there, including the limits
um and how that and and the parameters
and the guidelines.
But legislatively, what you're doing is
setting forth a requirement that
policies be drafted by the people that
are responsible for working with the
city funds on a daily basis and then
bringing them to you for approval and
obviously explaining them to make sure
that they meet with your approval before
they're initiated.
Um, it sets forth a requirement that um
all issuances of long debt long-term
debt must comply with the applicable
law.
um and must be approved by council by
ordinance. So again,
this would seem to be common sense, but
we want to make sure it's clear. The
city can't issue debt without you guys
approving it and approving it not only
by a motion, but by an ordinance, which
when we get into uh
se August and September, we'll talk
about ordinances, but um the charter
provides that ordinances just like
currently have to be read twice and go
through two meetings with the formality
for advertising. So, nothing's really
going to change there. The public's
going to have the opportunity to be
notified and come in and say we like
this or don't like this and for you guys
to have to receive comment on that um
before it's done.
Uh and then um there's a provision
regarding how investment of bond
proceeds should be handled. And again,
this is fairly standard by most bond
issuers and is best practices. There's
nothing there that is really new than
what we've been doing, but it's codified
into um administrative code for you.
Section five,
we move into the accounting system,
records and principles. Um,
obviously we need to have an accounting
system. It sounds like common sense, but
we want to make sure it's legislatively
required. Um, and we've put in uh what
we believe are both current practices
and best practices for what the
accounting system must do and should do
and how it should be set up, including
that it should be an electronic system.
It needs to be able to keep records. It
needs to be able to produce reports. It
needs to be able to maintain
distinctions with respect to the
character of expenditures. It must be
able to differentiate between funds. It
must be able to do all sorts of the
things that we need to do on an
accounting basis. Essentially, we need
to be able to have an accounting system
that complies with our auditor's reports
and and the internal controls that the
auditor sets forth based on generally
accepted accounting principles.
Um we codify the current method of
accounting that's been in place for
quite a long time and again is the
recommended method of accounting for
governmental entities which is uh an
accounting system on a modified acrruel
basis. Um it it talks about fund
accounting principles and policies and
we already talked about the funds. So
this explains now that the policies on
fund accounting and where that would tie
in. Um, again, for fund balance
requirements,
we're we're suggesting that the mayor
prepare with advice and consent of the
director of administrative services a
fund balance policy to establish how
balances the policies related to what
balances to keep in what funds at what
times under what parameters should be
drafted and brought to you for your u uh
review. Um
there these are things that the the
mayor and administrator should implement
and any policy under the that we're
going to in the next section of the code
we bring forth any any policies that are
adopted even when they're not they
they're internal and they don't
necessarily require council uh review or
consent. if they affect the public are
going to be uh we're suggesting that to
be required to be posted on the website
and readily available for all so
everybody knows how we operate and why
from a transparency and an accounting
standpoint.
Um
sectional six transactional processing.
So again this is really tying into the
accounting system but how do we get
things approved and processed? Um this
is really codifying our past practice
and current practice uh and common sense
like there's a multiple levels of
approval here um built into getting uh
transactions done. The the charter
already provides restrictions on
controller requiring a sign off before
uh checks are issued. So this is this is
not anything new. This is essentially
codification so everybody can understand
and see the actual practice.
We have set forth provisions regarding
some monthly fine monthly and quarter
end duties of the department of
administrative services regarding
reporting. Um some of these are are
pullouts from the charter and some of
them are expanded but essentially
there's monthly financial reporting um
and quarter end financial duties uh all
on a reporting end and then there's
year-end reporting. Uh and again this is
to asssure that all of the proper
procedures are looked at regularly
um by this council available to the
public. Um,
nothing more I can really say about
that. Um, section seven is warrants and
checks. Again, we need to gain a lot of
common sense here. We need to legislate
that yes, checks will be issued and
here's who they're signed by. Um, and
how it's done. Uh, one thing I'll note
here is um something that you won't see
in a lot of older administrative codes
because it didn't exist is the use of
electronic signatures um which were
we're suggesting be specifically
authorized here and that is common in
the banking world today. Um it is common
in the business world and it is also
common in the municipal world. So, it's
not something like we're breaking new
ground, but
section 8 obvious requires us to make
payroll and to process it. Um, again,
there's, you know, people that work for
you that, uh, need to be paid.
Um, section 9, uh, is really a new
provision. Um it codifies a lot of
what's been you've talked about and what
you've heard about in both audits
discussions with particularly uh Tina
and Director Campbell um regarding
capital um budgeting and capital
projects. It talks about the accounting
principles used to define what is a
capital project or a capital asset. So
that sometimes there's a lot of
confusion about that and this is a way
to to clarify utilizing generally
accepted accounting principles and for
those who aren't aware what that is um
in the professional accounting world
there is a nationwide standard of what's
called generally accepted accounting
principles. It's essentially what your
auditors are looking at when they look
at your records. Uh it's the covers both
internal controls and the functional
ways you record in your books
transactions. Um so that's supposed to
be a national best practices uh and it's
the standard that generally is applied
across the country.
Um
article 13 um procurement and disposal
of city property. So section one dealing
with the centralized coordinated
purchasing system um really is a pull
out direct and again this is again past
practice current practice but it's a
pull out both from the charter and your
optional third class city charter law.
This is essentially what we've been
operating under. It's a centralized and
coordinated purchasing system. The
procurement process and policies are
separate from the system. system is the
functional way in which uh
purchasing gets approved and or you know
a purchase is actually made like making
sure that it's approved by the right
people goes through the right accounting
steps and ultimately gets issued the
procurement process um this essentially
codifies what we're doing right now um
and is very consider and and is an
adoption which you're not required to do
it is an adoption in most places of the
third class city code and the way the
third class city code suggests doing
procurement. A couple things with
procurement are what the third class
city code does is say for different
types of purchases at different amounts,
we're going to require a different
different level of work on behalf of the
of the city. So for small purchases,
you don't have to go through this long
bidding process. You don't even have to
get estimates. You can use whom you want
as long as there's no fraud and
conflicts of interest. As you get into
moderate level, smaller, small but
moderate, you need to get three quotes,
right? And as you get to larger
contracts, you need to put them out for
bid. And it also incorporates all of the
exceptions to those that are built into
the third class city code because
there's a lot of contracts
that doesn't make that don't make sense
to go through that process. Sometimes
they um that don't make sense to be
required to go through that process is
the best way to put it. You know,
examples, the biggest examples are going
to be professional services contracts.
Um that doesn't mean that from a policy
standpoint.
City staff isn't encouraged to go
through RFPs and some sort of formal
process to identify parties, but
mandating it can sometimes put
hamstrings and handcuffs um on getting
the things done. So, um the the
exceptions that are built in here um are
the exceptions that are already in
practice in place. Um I will note
there's one that's added which is
emergency purchases.
Currently, the law without home rule
requires that it allows for an exception
for emergency purchase, but it puts the
standard of emergency to such that it's
virtually impossible. Um which means
it's not an exception. So, we There's
been added here a a an addition of an
emergency that's not part of a
declaration of emergency, which is two
different things. And a declaration of
emergency, we clearly want to be able to
go and purchase without going through
bidding. But there are times, and I can
use examples. Let let's let's say a
water man breaks and it requires a very
specific type of pipe to fix and we're
going to end up with millions of dollars
of loss of water. if we don't go to this
one company we know local that has the
pipe
right now we couldn't do that. We would
have to put it out for bid theoretically
unless we use one of the other
exceptions and there might be one there
but we would theoretically you'd have to
put it out for bid and that could take
months and in the meantime we're losing
one doesn't make a lot of sense. So
that's the only addition on to what
we're doing currently. And all of these
things again, everything in here is a
starting point for discussion. The fact
that we're doing it now doesn't mean it
can't be changed.
Doesn't mean it is just the starting
point when we put
um and you'll see what Angela's put up
on the screen is sort of the current
schedule. And what the third class city
code does is it adjusts this annually
with a department of labor labor and
industry um increase that they put in
place and we've included that annual
increase in here so that these numbers
will increase and then we would have to
update the schedule every year and it
would just become part of the code. So
that again from your standpoint,
uh, resident standpoint, taxpayer
standpoint, and those who are just
looking to say, I want to bid, but I
don't know what the policies are in the
city. Uh, it's going to be right here
legislated. You don't have to go and ask
for it.
Um,
you'll see in here in paragraph G, right
to reject bids or proposals. This is
built into every procurement, but we're
legislatively putting it in. So that now
there's no argument in a bid dispute
that we have that right. Again, this is
to protect the city, which is, you know,
if if your bid doesn't comply, we have
the right to reject it. Um, and the next
provision, charter liability limit. As a
matter of law, typically you can't enter
into a contract that doesn't have funds
allocated for it, right? So like if
contracts expend over year to year, this
is a provision that basically says all
of our contracts should include a
provision just like stateto state does
in the federal government. You have to
have funds allocated.
The the last section I mentioned at the
very outset we went through definitions
and this is sustainable procurement. Um
in 2019,
city the city adopted the um
uh city's municipal climate action plan.
This is a step towards trying to
implement it. There's no mandates here
about doing sustainable procurement.
There is a mandate that the procurement
office and city staff should start
considering in each of their
procurements whether there are means to
um uh get procurement that's better
environmentally. That was the first
definition that that and that is
sustainable over time. So these these
are things to start moving the the
climate action plan forward. Um again
not at the point of a mandate that
everything has to be sustainable or
environmentally protective. Um my
recommendation at this point is that
would be too restrictive and would
require new staffing to be able to even
get it accomplished. But to start
looking at it and building on it is
something I think it's the time to do.
Um it's consistent with this council's
directives over the last six years. So
that's why that's in here. And again,
these are suggestions as starting
points. Um sale and disposal of city
property. Um
sale of personal property. Right now,
any property would have to under the
third class city code, if it's $2,000,
we have to come to we have to get city
council's approval to sell anything. We
have to estimate its value. Um, and we
have to come forward with with your
consent. The proposal here is to tweak
that a little bit. Um, because we used
to hold annual surplus sale. There's
lots of stuff that becomes absolutely
useless to the city anymore. Um, and
that definition is included in here. And
where we have that, what we want to do
is authorize the director of
administrative services to to arrange
for a public sale um and or other
necessary sale of surplus materials. Uh
and that if it doesn't fall into that
then, you know, need council approval,
but it would all require advertising. Um
and you know, director of administrative
services
um and needs to formulate procedures for
this policies and procedures again so
everybody would know. sale of real
property. Essentially, this is just the
provision that you already have an
ordinance in place on this and it's
essentially incorporated uh the
ordinance in here. The exceptions built
both into that ordinance and and built
into here are the exceptions that are
currently provided for in the third
class city code. So again, that
ordinance was adopted was created and
adopted in accordance with third class
city code and it's just been brought in
uh to this document. Um, a new item is
the donations of both personal and real
property. Currently, it's very limited
as to what you can donate property and
how you can donate property. Um, which
has proven to be a bit cumbersome um for
entities that could really use it. Um,
and trying to scrape out $1,000 when it
would benefit the citizens much more to
have a service entity in the city be
able to utilize the property. So, we've
given you here some starting points for
discussion of those. Um, with personal
property, you know, uh, if it's valued
at $5,000 or less, director of
administrative services in accordance
with policies and procedures to be
adopted would be able to do that. Over
5,000 um, would need, you know, council
consent. So, I mean, having to come in
and ask, should we be um, do we give you
your consent to donate a maybe it's a
computer worth 50 bucks, maybe computer
worth a hundred um it just seemed to be
not to be an efficient way for you to
operate. So this is a procedure to try
to get efficiency and still protect make
protect the taxpayers to assure that you
know the assets of the city aren't being
gutted, right? Um and then donation of
real property. Um this requires approval
of council. Um and so this is you know
if if if a small piece of real estate is
better in the hands of an entity you
have to approve it which means that you
have to assure that you don't want to
get the money in lie of the donation you
have to make the costbenefit analysis.
Um it's not saying that the city's going
to go and donate property. Again this is
just legislating
um a process for doing that that doesn't
currently um exist.
So the last two sections are relatively
straightforward. Um again insurance and
bonding these are things that we
currently do. Um bonding is covered by
the third class city code. Insurance is
something we absolutely want to have
need to have and we want to make sure
that it's legislative directed
legislatively directed that we do have.
Um article 15 is really new. There is a
Pennsylvania records retention act. Um
what we're doing here is making sure
that we have an ordinance in place that
says we will comply. Um which is one of
the requirements of that act. Um and
directing that we comply with it. What
this really does is create schedules for
how you can destroy paper records
provided that you have electronic
copies. Right? And there's a whole
manual on that um based on the type of
record, the content of it as to when a
paper record can be destroyed. It
doesn't require that you destroy them.
It's just saying you can do it after
this period of time. And this is a state
act that governs municipalities
statewide.
Um and then record disclosure. This is
something we know we already have to do.
We have to comply with the right to know
law. And so we we've again legislatively
said not only do we know we have to do
it, but we're going to direct that we do
it. The city administration must comply
with the right to know law.
So, those are the provisions uh that I
wanted to present to you tonight. Um,
and I know you haven't had the
opportunity to read them. So, I've spent
45 minutes. Um, what I would like to do
is, you know, just ask Tina and the
mayor if they have any comments in terms
of the why we've put things in here and
then to open it up for discussion as to
why we have these. understanding that
you're going to now spend and so is the
public a significant amount of time
reviewing these going over the detail of
the language so that we can have really
good discussion uh next month at our
next meeting over hey why can't we make
a change to this shouldn't we add this
that's where I would expect to go in the
next meeting this is really for me to
explain to you what's here and answer
any questions as to why I might have
included it um or or as to the genesis
of it so that you have that
comprehensive understanding. So with
that, mayor, Tina, do you have anything?
I really don't except to say that um for
the public um who is listening uh who
wants to read and um ask questions or
make comments about any of the
administrative code topics that are
included in this first trunch um you can
go to engage Lancaster and there is a
section specifically to the admin code
uh to be able to read and comment and
submit your questions.
After each meeting, there'll be an open
comment period um for two weeks uh for
the public and we're also asking council
to submit your questions, but you're
going to be uh sent a jot form uh to
complete the questions and um that is so
that we don't um we avoid any potential
for a violation of Sunstein Act with two
or more of you potentially commenting.
Um, so we just want to make sure that we
are on the straight and narrow with
that. Um, as it relates to the content
that's presented tonight, I just want to
thank Barry and thank you for sitting
through a 45 minute lecture tonight. Um,
sorry to make it a lecture. Um, yeah, I
don't know how how to avoid it. Um, but
I think that the the main thrust of
tonight's conversation is just that
there's a lot of different places that
information is flowing into this
document. whether that's from the
charter itself, whether that's from the
state charter code, whether that's from
what what we've currently been doing, or
that it's it's new um and based on a
best practice that hasn't been adopted
um before, which goes to some of the um
uh reporting uh elements in the um
finance and budgeting as well as um
specification related to investments
that are allowable and those that would
be that would be ineligible. Um so um a
lot going into this document and as
Barry said nothing about this document
is written in stone. Um this is the
first trunch. We'll be bringing a second
um round to you in August. August
and then uh two discussion sessions and
then just to make sure everybody
understands there will be one vote on
the entire administrative code that will
be um is tenatively scheduled for
November. Um and uh that just is um just
to be clear that these are work sessions
and we're not taking any deliberative
action um during this time. It will be
introduced just like we do all all the
other things. It'll be a first reading,
a second reading, and a vote.
Tina. Yeah. Um
I
um I don't have a lot to add. I will
just say that um specifically the
sections around investment um debt and
cash reserves. Um they are as Barry
stated and the and the mayor um
emphasized as well. These are taken from
um either uh best practices uh practices
that we've already been doing. Um and
really the main uh focus that we pulled
it from is around um a organization
called GFOA which is the government
finance officers association. Um and so
they produce a lot of good guidelines
state specific as well as some national
guidelines. So we've been looking at
those. Um and I will just say uh for
those three sections in particular these
are not intended to be full policies.
They're intended to um kind of state
what the policies should have in them.
Um so we're still going to be bringing
policies to you all around these. Um but
this is really um kind of stating what
what is needed in those policies.
So you know from my perspective that
really sort of concludes what I wanted
to present to you tonight. Um, what I'd
like to do is just, you know, go around
and ask if you have any questions
regarding the presentation I made back
in June about home rule in general and
how it applies to this and about sort of
the the um broad philosophical topics
that we've addressed this evening. Um,
you know, as to specific language
questions, those I would I would prefer
we get into at the next session when we
can look at them in concert with others
because what ends up happening is when
you change one section, it sort of
snowballs across the board. So,
um, you know, with that, uh, council
president, I'll turn it back to you, but
that's where I would like to see, you
know, I I would suggest we take some
discussion tonight if if there is any.
Sure. Thank you, Barry. Um, I guess you
can tell me if this is broad enough or
if this is too specific. Sure. Um, and
and I'm looking at one particular
section, but I'll I'll make it broad.
So, in some of these sort of well,
particularly under the finance and
accounting uh sections, some of these
get very specific. And so
who ultimately is sort of responsible
for enforcement of these guidelines if
it's not something that like this is um
this quarterly report that needs to go
to council or this is a function that
needs to happen. So like can you speak
to how some of these processes work in
concert with maybe like employment
practices or HR practices? I'm not
really sure but well the financial ones
aren't going to really tie into to HR or
personnel. This is really the management
of money. Uh-huh. Um, it's the
administration's obligation to manage
the money in the way that these policies
andor provisions are set forth. The
reporting is intended to a make sure to
give you the ability to make sure
they're complying. Um, B, it gives the
auditor will be looking back at our
policies to say, are you actually
complying with your own requirements
which have been legislatively enacted?
Um obviously negative audit reports have
very negative um implications on the
city going forward. So there's an
incentive obviously for the
administration to do so. Um there will
be provisions I mean there's there
there are provisions at law that don't
get incorporated herein. Obviously
council can end up with a dispute with
another elected official. So I mean
there have been municipalities where the
mayor and council have been vehemently
at odds. uh and it's resulted in
litigation and council has the right to
seek litigation to direct the
administration to comply with the rules
and regulations if they're not. So
ultimately um you have the power to
compel um the procedure and how you do
it is going to be a little bit left to
counsel based on the facts if that makes
sense. Like you know I I don't always
recommend litigation. I would hope that,
you know, if you see something that's
not being done, um, the adults in the
room can have a conversation and get to
a place of concurrence on how to move
forward. Acknowledging that in not all
of the municipalities across the
Commonwealth, has that always happened?
Sure. Okay, that makes sense. Thank you
very much. Um, we'll just go around as
we're sitting, uh, if that's okay.
That's good. Any thoughts, Council
Craig?
my uh the only question that I have is
along with the charter and the
information that we're given here
um am I going to be able to find
like all pro most of the answers that I
need and if I can't find the answers
that I need who I call or do I need a
book like yours? Well, um you don't need
a book. uh the person that's going to
get you the answers is sitting in front
of you and speaking to you. Um I'm not
hiding anything from you. I I will not
hide anything from you. Um that's not my
role here. My role is to get you a
document that works for you. Um I will
tell you very clearly where a language
came from, why it was put here. Um you
don't have to go searching for it. Um
the reality is that you really don't
need to read any of the other things.
You need to read this if you if you want
ideas. There's a third class city code,
there's a first class city code, there's
a secondass city code, there's a first
class township code, a secondass
township code. You know, there are
multiple municipal codes where these
types of things have been dealt with.
Um, so the beauty here is because you're
home rule, you're drafting your own
code. So there's no right, there's no
wrong other than we have to comply with
the charter and we have to comply with
the constitutional requirements of
Pennsylvania and any state requirements
that the legislature has put in place.
So for example, there are some laws that
we can't deviate from like we are we are
required to comply with things like the
public utility laws. We can't change
those. They govern every and all
municipalities, right? Um, eminent
domain rules are governed by an eminent
domain code that applies to every
municipality regardless of of home rule
or not. Um, so the reality here is
you're you're starting from scratch. And
so the the concept that we did we came
for came up with in order to present you
with a code was to give you a code that
is balanced by this is what you've been
doing. We've been doing it for decades
either under the third class city code,
the optional third class city charter
law. Um that contains provisions that
are required by the charter and that
offers some new language or new ideas um
from our role within the city and
watching the city grow over the years.
Perfect. Thank you. Thank you, councelor
Craig. Councelor Klest. Thank you, Madam
President. Uh so I haven't read it yet
so I don't have uh really many questions
but I was looking at um section one
where we have the definitions
and how did you come up with those
concept or where did you get them
because I know that we have other
concepts for example like um the
department below office sometimes we
said for example uh um the Bureau of
Lancaster, the police bureau of lan city
Lancaster of Lancaster or for example we
said the department of uh administrative
services or the department of
neighborhood engagement we have offices
we have boards, commissions,
authorities. Those items aren't covered
in in the definitions. Those are covered
by the charter and then by your own
ordinances. So um one of the things that
you'll see in the next trunch will be
one of the requirements of the five that
that the charter requires is a breakout
essentially of the departments bureaus
administrative units and their
responsibilities. So those will each be
discussed to some extent in the next
section that you haven't seen yet. The
definitions are terms that are
referenced in various places in the code
that one might not really have an
understanding or might not be explained.
So, um, you know, we we use the term
confidential information. Okay, if I say
confidential information, what's that
mean? Well, the definition section was
meant to cover that. Um, some of the
state laws so that we don't have to
write out the citation for the entire
state law are built into the
definitions, but they're ones that that
and where I got them is I defined the
term, whether that was a term that's
utilized by law, the specific
definition, or a term that I wrote as
being the definition.
So after reviewing it, so we we all
going to read it.
Can we add the order definitions of
order? You can you can add or delete
anything from this document. This is
your document, not my document. Okay.
Thank you. That's all I have for now.
Thank you, councelor colleagues.
Councelor Royo, thoughts. I don't have
any questions or comments to see. Thank
you. Thank you. Uh councelor Diaz,
thoughts, questions?
I just have one question regarding the
transfers. You're saying that it's 5% of
the funds in the budget line items. Does
it matter how much it is? Like if it's
in the millions, it's 5% of that
particular amount. Yeah. When you're
referring to that there and that's the
current that's been the current practice
and that's and that's only for
transferring it from one department to
another. it's not authorizing it to be
to be spent in a uh you know to to
change the fact that you've already
authorized it to be spent. Um and this
is again I that provision is really
relating to to transfers between
departments and so that we can't
transfer more than uh you know 4%
essentially or 5% without council
approval and and even when they are
transferred there's a reporting
requirement to notify council that they
have. Yeah. And it doesn't allow for an
increase to the overall budget. It's
just a transfer between the departments.
So that's the final amount like it can
the charter change it. Let's say you
want to change it to like 10%. Again,
the provisions in this code, every one
of them is changeable. Okay. Thank you.
Thank you, councelor Med. Thoughts and
questions.
There you go. Uh thank you, Council
President. And uh thank you uh Barry for
your um presentation this evening. Um
and I really appreciate some of the good
governance measures um around
procurement and around uh the budgets.
Um I guess my only question and guidance
um that I would like to seek throughout
this process is you know how much of
this should we leave kind of um not
specifically defined and how much should
we for example when it comes to things
like accounts like how like should we
make sure that each individual fund has
its own individual account and does
payroll have its own individual account
or are these things that we should kind
of leave um by your recommendation as a
little bit less specific and like you
know the charter gives us the guidance
but how specific on some of these things
should we go in the code? Sure. My my
recommendations are what's in the what's
in the code before you? Um and they're
in part based on past practices. They're
in part based on the thirdass city code.
Um they're in part based on my
experience with other municipalities as
their solicitor. and they're in part
based on my experience seeing where
other municipalities have struggled. Um
the the the one thing that um is here is
you always will have the flexibility to
get it more specific. So because this is
an ordinance, you have the ability to
always change. My recommendation and and
this is simply a recommendation is that
what we're putting forward putting
forward before you starts to make
changes. it doesn't necessarily overturn
the entire apple cart. Um, and that as
you see issues arise, that's the time to
address by legislation because you do
control it. If there's no reason, you
know, it's the old saying, don't fix
what's not broken. At the same time, you
want to put best management places in
place to encourage change to get better.
If something is a problem, address it.
Um what's built into the code that we're
presenting you tonight and then we'll
continue to present to you in August are
the recommendations that were meant to
balance those in all honesty. Um there
are some things we're recommending
changes to. Um we could have been as
broad in here on financial policies as
the mayor should adopt policies that
could have sat satisfied the charter,
but my recommendation is to go far
beyond that. Right. um that it does make
sense to have some legislative
understanding of what those policies
should have in them, what the basic
requirements should be, and then to let
the professionals go to work to develop
the policies based on the specific facts
that the city is undertaking. And so
that's how I've drafted this for you.
And um so I think it's going to be a
case- by case basis as to whether you
feel there's something that needs to be
more specific. And that's what I think
these discussions should happen as we
move forward into the next session. But
yes, and and councelor Med, I would just
add to that. Um
I think you uh you should just also
consider about what kind of work you
want to have come before council on a
regular basis. So, with uh setting up
accounts, uh when we get a grant, um so
we just got a $35,000 grant from the
Ches Bay um trust, I believe, and that
would have its own individual account.
Do you want that level of detail coming
before council on a monthly basis or are
you satisfied with there being a
reporting structure in place such that
um on a monthly basis income uh and
expenses are being shown and that
financial report is given to council.
And so I think you have to decide for
yourselves h how you want to be spending
your time uh in terms of the regular
business of council versus what is
already being pulled together in a
financial report. and also recognize
that that is the purpose of our annual
audit and engaging with the audit
process I think is one of the primary
tasks of council in addition to um
overseeing and um passing the budget.
And so it is through the audit process
that we have to apply we have to prove
that we are following uh gazby standards
as it relates to our financial
management. So, I think you just have to
decide kind of like how specific you
want to go and then think about where
where this might this thread might be
getting picked up in other areas that
are already coming to council. And and
one thing I should note and again this
is one of the reasons I suggested um
really taking a close look at the
charter is the charter actually provides
a very a very expanded role of the city
controller uh in um being a guide and uh
a guide with respect to financial
policies. um additional checks and
balances on not only um whether funds
are authorized but on the the
implementation and follow-through of
policies on the selection of the um
annual of the auditor to perform the
annual audit. Um so again um it's a
continuation of building additional
internal controls. Um, you know, and
fortunately the city's not been the
subject of any municipal sort of fraud
uh for as long as I've been around and
and and hopefully it goes on forever.
Um, but it's best practice is to
continue to make sure the internal
controls are in place.
Uh, thank you. And I just have one final
question and it's kind of in regards to
like um what this new charter and some
of the ambiguities of what state law is
currently, what state laws may change.
Um, is there anything in the
administrative code that we could kind
of put in to protect I don't want to say
protect the city and council but so that
every for instance every other day
somebody isn't saying oh this state law
actually you can do this or council
should do this because of this state law
um when it's kind of responsible
governance to not just act on everything
just because we have the yeah I
councelor I really appreciate that
question and if only if only there was
that much activity in Harrisburg that
actually affected our local government.
We could we could have that
conversation, but I can tell you there's
not that much uh that actually on a
regular basis affects the operations of
local government. Uh boy, do I wish
sometimes sometimes I wish be careful
what you wish for, right? Yeah. the the
the other place uh Councilman that that
that you have control over that is keep
in mind that the act is most likely
going to be legislative that you're
taking. So that's certainly the question
that council should be asking every time
an ordinance has come before it is have
we confirmed have we checked do is there
do we believe that there's any state law
prohibiting the question is is there any
state law or constitutional requirement
prohibiting us from taking the action
that we're proposing by this ordinance
and each one of them does state you know
it will take effect in accordance with
all applicable state and local laws
which you know we get used to hearing
that but it is truly like catching
statement on all of our legislation. It
is um and you know, one of the things
that you will see when we get to August
is um a suggestion, a recommendation for
uh some additional documentation that
should come to council and the public
with every presented ordinance, whether
that comes directly from council or the
administration. Um, and I gave a
presentation that started to go into
that a number of years ago about uh the
types of things that should be looked
at, thought of, and and asked, questions
asked when an ordinance is adopted. Um,
and I've worked with that to parro it
down a little bit. Um, instead of 12
questions, I think it'll end up being
maybe four or five. Um, but the point
being is it's it's sort of following a
state process of having a memo in place.
Um and and it's that process that gives
council members now and in the future
assurances um that at least it's been
looked at. One thing I'll say is the law
does change. It can change by a court
decision. Um and you no matter how good
your lawyer is, lawyers can be wrong. Um
we can have an opinion that this is what
the law says and somebody can challenge
it and the court can be different. So
the the the real thing is and and that's
not to try and say and discou my duty,
but the reality it's a it's a factual
reality. Um so the main thing is to make
sure that you're doing the due diligence
to make educated decisions about what
your ordinances do and whether um and
again I don't say whether you're
authorized. The key is whether you're
prohibited. Um because that's really the
real change with home rule.
Thank you. And that concludes my
questions. Thank you. Great. I I have
one last thought of my own and I just
want to well thank you for putting this
together. I particularly appreciate the
tables that are uh included on the
budget timeline and the other timelines
because reading through that in the way
it is presented in the charter is
complicated to follow. Um it was
complicated to put the tables together
you can imagine. U so I appreciate that.
Thank you very much.
Um, so, uh, at this time we can, uh,
open up the meeting for public comment.
I'll just remind folks if they wish to
make comment, they're commenting on, uh,
anything that was presented before us
this evening. If anyone wishes to do so,
you can do so at the microphone at the
far end of the table. Um, it should be
on and ready for you. And you need to
begin with your name and your block of
residence for our meeting record and
three minutes, which I'll time on my
phone this evening. So if anyone wishes
to do so, now is the time.
Okay.
All right.
All right. Good evening. You'll have to
take my word that I'm timing. So, uh,
good evening. Uh, my name is Alexander
King. I live in the 600 block of North
Shippen. And, um, I have a couple
questions. One of them is on the
procurement um
numbers and I was a bit surprised to see
that the threshold for a a public bid is
just 23,000 and change. That that seems
like a pretty small sum for what strikes
me as a fairly involved and ownorous
procedure. I was curious is that state
law requiring that um or is there room
to wiggle on that? And then if I can
just the other comment I just give them
both to you. um is um speaking of money,
there has been a lot of talk in the last
year and a half or so about um council
salaries and um I don't know if you want
to address that as part of the
administrative code, but I think it
would be an excellent idea to make a
plan on how council is going to increase
salaries that haven't been increased in
a very long time so that there is some
sort of plan in place and it's not this
always like Oh, should we do this? Uh,
no. I don't want to anger the
electorate. Should we do this? No, I
don't want to anger the electorate.
That, you know, something should really
be done there. That's that's Thank you
very much, Mr. King. Uh, Mr. Hamburger,
if you want to answer the those those
questions uh that were put forth. Sure.
Um, the as I indicated uh during the
procurement discussion, the the
thresholds are the the current thirdass
city law. Um, those are in place for
third class cities. While we're not
mandated to comply with those going
forward, uh it's my recommendation that
we do. And while that number seems low,
um what it's doing is assuring that
taxpayer dollars are getting the best
best service um that it can for the
dollars being spent. The procurement
process and the thresholds do more than
just the money. Um, we've we've
experienced here at the city that when
we use public procurement, we find
opportunities we didn't know existed,
vendors we didn't know might be
available, um, and ideas and concepts
that we might not have thought of. So
procurement is more than just simply how
we spend the money. But the methodology
forces us to be open um and to make sure
that we are doing due diligence um for
the taxpayers, residents, and those who
use city services.
Um as to uh council salaries, um the uh
the mechanism for how to do that is
built into the charter and the
administrative code as we discussed
tonight. Whether council wants to adopt
an ordinance or develop a plan for when
to adopt an ordinance for changes in in
elected official salaries, that's
certainly up to council. Thank you, Mr.
Hanburgger. Um, just to kind of put a
finer point on the the bid public bid
threshold, the these could be a a myriad
of services and contracts that we're
talking about from like sort of like
one-time transactions and and to ongoing
contracts as well. Is that correct?
Okay. Thank you. Any additional public
comment this evening?
Good evening. Good evening. Um Oh, you
might have to turn that back on.
Shut it off.
That sounds like it was on. Can you hear
me? Yeah. Great. Um Marshall Miller,
100th block of East Vine Street. Um, it
sounds like the final version of this
will be voted on in November. And I was
just curious, um, how council has the
ability to put like input, changes,
things of that nature leading up to the
final passage or is it just final
passage in November will be a process
where amendments are added to all of the
changes that council would like to see?
Um, separately, uh, you said that this
document pulls from a bunch of different
sources and I'm just curious if there is
like a version of the document that
outlines what coming directly from the
charter that cannot be changed or you
know touched because it has to fulfill
requirements in the charter and if that
exists that would be helpful for me to
see and probably council as well. Uh the
the answers to those are there is no
real document that does the detail
you're asking for. Everything in this
document can be touched. So again, there
are multiple sources from where we drew
inspiration for the language. Um, in
terms of the topics that are covered,
there's mandatory topics. The language
other than the parts that come directly
from the charter, it's it's all brand
new um essentially or it's a repeat of
existing code. But it's sources that
were drawn from. There's no one document
I can give you that will tell you where
to go find um every single line that's
in this document. Um it's it's a new
ordinance. Um it's a new draft just like
any other new ordinance that city
council would adopt. That being said,
there are four working sessions. Um
there's a procedure that uh the mayor
discussed and will be available for
council members and the public to submit
questions. Um at the second session um
uh in a month um we'll work with
consensus. So, if this group by
consensus says, "Hey, we, you know," and
that's more than less is what we mean by
consensus because ultimately there's
still a vote at the tail end, um, we'd
like to see, you know, maybe uh, this
changed to that or this added or this
taken down. Um, we'll make those changes
and and circulate them. Mr. Hamburger,
can I elaborate on that just to kind of
just drill into the process? This is for
everybody's benefit. So what we're
having, what we have is four work
sessions in front of us. They're not
legislative. And so that format will
allow us to have the kind of discussion
that's needed about this document. Um
that will not require motions and
amendments and and for every detail,
right? because that would be required if
that's if we were given this document in
its form uh motioning that forward and
then opening up that discussion uh that
would that would be ownorous. And so
these work sessions are going to allow
us to have that kind of conversation and
the format first a presentation with
general comments, impressions, a period
of time where questions are to be
received both by the public and by
members of council and then a second
session where we come back and sort of
put those out on the table and work for
toward consensus. uh during discussion
uh will allow us to have a finished
product that will come forward in the
legislative process where there's a
first reading and a second reading and
you know not to say that there couldn't
be amendments at that time but hopefully
in four working sessions where we have
actual real discussion uh we should be
ready to to adopt the the document that
we've worked on uh over the course of
those four meetings. That answers my
question perfectly. Thank you. Thanks.
Any additional comments from the public?
All right, hearing none. Thank you
everyone. I will close public comment
for this evening. I believe that
concludes what we needed to work on in
this session. Mr. Henburgger, Mayor
Sarra, is that correct? From my
perspective, absolutely. I thank you for
your time. Thank you. Um then I will
hear a motion to adjurnn.
Second. We have a motion and a second.
All in favor? I I thank you. You're
adjourned.
I want to have my gabble.